<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A nevv instuction [sic] of plowing and setting of corne, handled in manner of a dialogue betweene a ploughman and a scholler Wherein is proued plainely that plowing and setting, is much more profitable and lesse chargeable, than plowing and sowing. By Edvvard Maxey. Gent.</title>
            <author>Maxey, Edward, Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07301</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17695</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113159</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848398</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848398</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13488</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07301)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13488)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1606:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A nevv instuction [sic] of plowing and setting of corne, handled in manner of a dialogue betweene a ploughman and a scholler Wherein is proued plainely that plowing and setting, is much more profitable and lesse chargeable, than plowing and sowing. By Edvvard Maxey. Gent.</title>
                  <author>Maxey, Edward, Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Felix Kyngston, dwelling in Pater noster Rowe, ouer against the signe of the Checker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Running title reads: A new instruction of plowing and setting of corne.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ E³.</note>
                  <note>Some pages closely cropped, affecting marginal print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:1"/>
            <p>A NEW INSTVCTION OF PLOWING AND SET<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TING OF CORNE, HANDLED IN MANNER OF A DIALOGVE betweene a Ploughman and a <hi>Scholler.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is proued plainely that Plowing and</hi> Setting, is much more profitable and leſſe chargeable, than Plowing and Sowing.</p>
            <p>By EDVVARD MAXEY. Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He that withdraweth the Corne, the people will curſe him: but bleſsing ſhall be vpon the head of him that ſelleth Corne.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 11.26.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>men ploughing with horses and setting a field</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Felix Kyngston,</hi> dwelling in Pater noſter Rowe, ouer againſt the ſigne of the Checker. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIPFVL SIR RICHARD MARTEN KNIGHT, MASTER OF HER MAIESTIES MYNT, ALDERMAN, <hi>and twiſe Lord Maior of the Citie of London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowne (right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull) how great a benefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and furtherer you haue been to many good workes and profitable to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: for by your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, the inhabitants of ſundrie parts of England and Wales, haue gained for many yeeres, many thouſand pounds yeerely. How much then thoſe poore are bound to praiſe God for you, and ſuch as further the like good works, all wiſe men acquainted with your great charge and trauell can teſtifie, which I thought worthy to be publiſhed, and left in memorie for other ages yet to come, to your great commendation and incouragement of others, to follow your good example. And now (right Worſhipfull) calling to minde my former time ſpent in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie;
<pb facs="tcp:13488:3"/>the moſt ſweete and comfortable kind of life to all vertuous minds (that <hi>Adams</hi> poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie can enioy) if it were not for the wickednes of ſeruants, who diſcourage many induſtrious minds; and ſeeing an vnskilfull Pamphlet (cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>God ſpeede the Plough</hi>) to be ſo long vnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, ſet foorth by ſome Nouice in Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie, as ſhould appeare as well by his writing, as that he ſaith in the ſame, it is none of his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; which hath and may doe much hurt by diſſwading men from ſo profitable an imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the ſetting of Corne; which when I conſidered, and remembring that I had ſpent the moſt part of thirtie yeeres in Husbandrie: I aduentured to publiſh this little Treatiſe, for the inſtruction of thoſe that will be perſwaded to practiſe this kind of excellent and profitable worke: which with my ſelfe I deſire to be protected by your accuſtomed lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing fauour towards me.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours to be commaunded, <hi>EDVV. MAXEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas there are two bookes written con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſetting of Corne: the firſt commending it, the ſecond diſgracing it; both of them diſcourſing ſo Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerlike, that the plaine Countrie Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band man, cannot iudge which of them hath moſt skill for inſtruction in this kinde of Husbandrie; and perceiuing that the ſecond treatiſe (called <hi>God ſpeede the Plough</hi>) hath diſſwaded great numbers from the practiſe of ſetting of Corne: I was aduiſed and reſolued to aduenture the publike cenſuring of this Inſtruction. Wherein I deſire to proue how much more caſie and profitable, Plowing and Setting will be in all places, and that with leſſe charge, then either Plowing and Sowing, or digging and Setting, deſiring to be freed from all ſuſpition, to contend for art or learning with any of the former writers. And like a plaine Ploughman to ſhew my opinion, what I thinke of the former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, betweene the Plowe and the ſpade: in a word, I iudge both theſe profitable inſtruments may right well be vſed in their proper places, that the Plowe may keepe his place in the fields,<note place="margin">A little good counſel would haue ſaued all your labour in writing, and mine in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering: but I: hope it will doe good.</note> to the great increaſe of Corne, and the Spade in the Gardens for rootes, hearbs, and flowers, neceſſarie for houſehold prouiſion. And I could haue wiſhed you the Gentleman and author of the booke (called <hi>God ſpeede the Plowe</hi>) had taken better coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of ſome skilfull Husbandman, before you had publiſhed a
<pb facs="tcp:13488:4"/>booke, wherein you indeuour to correct and teach an Arte, which you acknowledge is none of your profeſsion, &amp; to haue conſidered how eaſelie for the moſt part our Engliſh Nation are diſſwaded from good cauſes, neither for the glorie of God, or the honour and profit of their Prince and Countrie: for though it be true, that very fewe innouations in the Church, or nouelties in a ſtate, are not alwaies and generallie good, and profitable for all places, and for all people: yet theſe profitable inuentions, ſpeciallie in Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, ſhould rather be commended then diſgraced, vntill a manifeſt error in them be diſcouered, and that by experience and proofe. Againe, you ought rather to haue remembred and well conſidered the lamentable caſe of the poore that liued in diſtreſſe in the late yeeres of dearth, who notwithſtanding the charitable orders taken by her Maieſtie, her honorable Counſell and other officers of the kingdome, to the glorie of God, and their high commendation: yet was it well ſeene with the eyes of the trulie charitable, that except the King of heauen and earth had relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the poore people of this Land, with Corne out of his ſtorehou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in other Countries; the poore and the rich alſo had been in hazard to haue periſhed by famine, that might haue fallen vpon this ſinfull people, or by ſome wofull calamities, inſeparable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions of penurie and want. And let euery indifferent man conſider what huge quantities of Corne may yeerely be ſaued, that now is caſt away by Plowing and Sowing: yet giue me leaue plainelie to giue you a proiect what this would come vnto. Some writers of our time account but nine thouſand ſixe hundred and two and fiftie Pariſhes, or thereabouts, in England, and ſuppoſe ſixe hundred and two and fiftie of them to be in Cities and Townes vſing no Tyllage: and ſo account but nine thouſand Countrie Pariſhes, and becauſe the author of the booke (called <hi>God ſpeede the Plough</hi>) writeth, that if a Pariſh haue three thouſand Acres of erable land, which is about thirtie or fortie Ploughlands in a Pariſh, therefore miſtruſting his iudgement,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:4"/>we will admit but ten Plowelands, one Pariſh with another; ſo nine thouſand Pariſhes hath foure ſcore and ten thouſand Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands, and that if in euery Ploweland there may eaſely be ſaued yeerely ten or twelue quarters of Seede Corne, that now is caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, which ſhall be directly proued, it will amount to ſome nine or ten hundred thouſand quarters of Graine that might euery yeere be ſaued in her Maieſties dominions: I dare affirme ſo much (be it more or leſſe) as would fetch hither the Indies Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure out of Spaine and other Countries farre diſtant; to the great honour and riches of our Prince and Countrie, and eſpeciallie the maintenance of our Engliſh Nauie, with plentifull prouiſion alſo of victuals for Souldiers both by Sea and Land, to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding comfort, and the terror of all forraine enemies.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, I wiſh that they whoſe hearts the Lord hath endewed with true wiſedome, and charitie, to remember and conſider well of this danger, from which the Lord hath ſo lately deliuered vs: and let vs all ſerue that God in the moderate vſe of his creatures, and not conſume in riotous gluttonie and drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kennes, ſuch great quantities of his bleſsings, to the hurt of our bodies and ſoules, the poore being readie to famiſh before our eyes. So I commend thee good Christian Reader, to Gods protection, and this worke to the bleſsing of the Almightie.</p>
            <p>The particular proofes of this good Husbandrie, ſhall be ſeene in a dialogue, betweene a Ploughman and a Scholler, for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtruction of plaine Countrie people.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:5"/>
            <head>A NEW INSTRVCTION OF PLOWING AND SETTING OF CORNE, HANDLED IN manner of a Dialogue betweene a <hi>Ploughman and a Scholler.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing I am appoynted to defend the profitable arte of ſetting of Corne, though in reſpect of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning very vnfit, yet becauſe I haue profeſſed and practized Husban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie for the moſt part of thirtie yeeres, and that you, the author of the booke (called <hi>God ſpeede the Plough</hi>) ſay that husbandrie is no part of your profeſſion, I may hope to maintaine againſt you by way of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in plaine Husbandrie, that Plowing and Setting is much better and more profitable, than either Plowing and Sowing, or Digging and Setting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>I maruell that my booke doth ſo much of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend you, I thought to haue pleaſed you and all Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, for ſo commending the olde faſhion of Plowing and Sowing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>Surely ſir you haue no otherwiſe offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me, than all other men that deſire the good of their Countrie, and be ſorie to ſee the ſimple abuſed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by your meanes, and how you pleaſe an other
<pb facs="tcp:13488:6"/>ſort of wilfull men, that will neither know what may be profitable for themſelues, nor haue any ſuch heartie loue to their Countrie and poore neighbours, as they ought to haue. As for your booke, howſoeuer you meant, it ſerues to ſo little good purpoſe (in my conceite) that it was the chiefe cauſe that moued me to take this worke in hand, to correct (if it were poſſible) the euill humors and preiudicate opinions againſt Corne-Setting, that it hath planted in mens heads and hearts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>I am ſorie that my booke ſhould breede any euill humors in mens heads or hearts, and I pray you what faults doe you finde in my booke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>Sir there be faults too many, which being the fruites of your idle houres (as you ſay) be not much to be marueiled at, for ſeldome doth idlenes bring forth any profite in husbandrie. And it is not my purpoſe to expoſtulate with you vpon all particular faults; they are too many to trouble the reader with: but you ſhall heare mine opinion, like a man of my plaine profeſſion, &amp; I will tell you my minde what I doe thinke in this argument, as well as I can. To paſſe ouer other matters, I will begin to defend our old faſhion of Ploughes, againſt your ſtrange Plough, that you ſay <hi>might be ſo made and handled, that it may goe deeper by a foote more than ordinarie, proportioning the ſtrength of the Teeme and Plough together.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Note that the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the olde faſhion Ploughes and this ſtrange Plough, is but to proue the Plough apt to ſet Corne.</note>Sir, if you can deuiſe a Plough that will goe deeper in all grounds (for you make no difference) a foote more than ordinarie, it were good you brought it forth; for ſurely it is likely to proue an implement of great force to our Engliſh Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie: for with it you muſt be compelled to plowe land twentie inches deepe or thereabouts, and yet I muſt confeſſe to my remembrance, I neuer ſaw any Plough, though drawne with ten oxen, to goe aboue eight or ten
<pb facs="tcp:13488:6"/>inches ordinarilie, and that with much a doe; and I pray you, how many Oxen or Horſe will your Plough require to be drawne with? for in ſome places if you make it goe, we plaine countrie men will ſuſpect you will Coniure: and in many places the qualitie of the mould will not permit our ten inches, much leſſe your two and twentie. Againe, what vſe I pray you ſhall the Common-wealth haue of ſuch an implement, where either it cannot goe vnles the diu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ell draw it, or may not goe for the euill mould it will turne vp? and ſo your Plough in that place doth more harme, than your booke can doe good any where elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo ſir, I will haue my Teeme and my Plough ſo made, that it ſhall goe well of that depth in ſuch grounds, as I will chuſe to ſet my Corne in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>It may be poſſible (if it pleaſe God to worke ſuch wonders by your inuention) but we the poorer ſort of Husbandmen, cannot make Ploughs, and prouide Teemes of that value and qualitie; neither haue we ſuch change of Land, as to make choyſe of apt grounds to beare the weight of ſuch Plowes &amp; Teemes; but I doubt not by Gods helpe, to plowe and dreſſe ten Acres of Land, as well as you ſhall doe with your ſtrange Plough, or any man ſhal do with a ſpade, except he digge it two ſpit deepe, &amp; ſo burie the firſt ſpit with the ſecond, which wil be both extreme chargeable and impoſſible in moſt grounds; and yet where he may digge but one ſpit, there will remaine needes vnburied ſpecially the Cooch, which I neuer ſaw deſtroyed, but with a ſommer fallow, or burning the land, as the Deuonſhire men doe: the which killing of weedes, howſoeuer it can be done, is the chiefe cauſe, that vpon extreame barren Land, thoſe countrie people haue good Corne, which otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:13488:7"/>
                  <note place="margin">The deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of weedes, a chiefe poynt in Husbandry.</note>ſhould haue little or none: and I deſire all good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands to conſider how neceſſarie it is for them to deſtroy the weedes, before they ſowe or ſet their Corne, that (if poſſiblie they can) they ſuffer not the weeds to ſucke out the ſappe of their grounds in the ſpring time, and all ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, before they commit their ſeede to the ground, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering it with ſuch enemies, which they may doe (in my opinion) by one or two plowings more in their ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fallow aboue ordinarie, if the weedie condition of the Land, or the ſeaſon of the yeere doe require it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſir, admit you doe plowe your Land as well as the Spade can doe it, as deepe as your Plough will goe, yet as I ſay, you cannot plowe it deepe enough, nor lay it leuell and plaine for the ſetters to worke vpon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Corne ſowed aboue furrow, often lieth not one inch deepe.</note>To this I anſwere, firſt that I will plow it deepe enough, for what ſhould ſet my Corne to grow as well, and much better (being ſet in due proportion &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der) when it hath as much hollow &amp; looſe ground vnder him, to ſpread roote and lie pleaſantly in, as your booke or the former appoynts, or as our ſowne Corne euer had, ſince ſowing was firſt vſed, and that is but three or foure inches deepe: and as farre as I know, our engliſh Corne rooteth not paſt two or three inches directly downwards. So then, if it roote downewards, and ſpring vpwards but fiue or ſixe inches at the moſt; meruaile why you ſhould thinke I ſhould not plowe it deepe enough, when your ſelfe faith you will plowe it yet deeper by a foote more if neede be, and I pray you ſo do, but take heede you meete not with thoſe furious beaſts you ſpeake of in your book,<note place="margin">This Plough will ſerue to make ditches, but for the danger of thoſe beaſts.</note> that will deuoure the Corne when it lieth ſo deepe and light, for if they catch you and your Plough (in moſt grounds of England) they would ſurely deuoure your Plough, and put your perſon in great hazard, without
<pb facs="tcp:13488:7"/>ſpeedie helpe: and therefore we will not plow ſo deepe, it is good ſleeping in a whole skin. But if you had been contented with halfe a foote more then ordinarie, there had been ſome poſſibilitie in ſome places, yet with much adoe: therfore I pray you giue ſome men leaue, that haue or may haue good Teemes &amp; Ploughs, though not made after your faſhion, to goe but two or three inches more than ordinary, &amp; then they may plow ſome ten or twelue inches with much adoe where the land will permit, ſo if our Corne haue fiue or ſixe inches to ſpring vpward, (euen from the lower moſt part of his roote) and as much downward, it ſhall be ſufficient to content vs with the increaſe of eyght or ſixe quarters vpon an Acre:<note place="margin">Note well.</note> doe you plowe it deeper for thirtie or twentie quarters vpon an Acre (God ſend it you that venter ſo deepe for it.) And as for laying our ground leuell and plaine, we will not follow your counſell in your booke, nor feare your woodden dagger, your huſwife-like inſtructions are to rake away the graſſe that the light Harrow leaueth, till it be as leuell as a Garden, and then to ſet it; as though any good husband would haue his Land ſo out of tilth, and ouergrowne with weedes, that at ſowing or ſetting time, the Land ſhould neede the raking of the graſſe, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a good ſommer fallowe. It is time for ſuch a Plough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to throwe his Plough in the hedge, and take the Spade in hand, and become one of your threeſcore labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers: and then in the fame place you tell vs of laying it as leuell as a Garden. And I pray you ſir, then what ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the Corne of the beſt and moſt grounds of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, ſpeciallie for Wheate and Rie?<note place="margin">Winter Corne cannot lie too hie in moſt grounds.</note> For if you leuell it ſo like a Garden, without all queſtion, it will be drowned for the moſt part, &amp; come to little or no good at all, for all men I thinke that euer ſaw Husbandrie, or vnderſtoode
<pb facs="tcp:13488:8"/>naturall reaſon, know that ſuch Land; nay, moſt Land muſt be laide high and round with furrowes, according to the qualitie of the ſoile, or elſe the ſeede will be drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And to breake the clods, we may vſe the Rowler, as we doe for our Barlie if neede be, and ſo much ſhall ſerue for inſtruction, or rather perſwaſion of ſuch as you haue inueigled with ſo many idle doubts, in a matter that may be perceiued by thoſe that are not wilfullie blinde, or not skilfull at all in Husbandrie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo ſir, theſe are not altogether ſo idle as you make them, but I pray you how will you make this barren Land rich enough, to haue ſuch increaſe as will anſwere the charge of ſetting?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede that is not altogether ſo idle as the other, but yet very eaſie to be anſwered, and very likelie to be compaſſed, euen in the barreneſt Countries and places farre remoued from all meanes to enrich their Land. Here then I would aduiſe all good Husband-men that intend ſetting, to lay all their ſoile and foule doung that they vſed to ſcatter ouer thirtyAcres or there abouts, (being their ordinarie ſeaſon) I ſay, lay it vpon ten Acres. And by reaſon they leaue twentie Acres to reſt, they ſhall keepe more ſtore of Sheepe either of their own, or take to folde of other mens, and ſo keep them better, and by that meanes their folde will be much bigger, and their Land will be folded much better: and if there be any Marle of Chalke, or of other ſort of good molde neere to be had by any meanes, they ſhall now haue leaſure to fetch it, by reaſon they haue ſo little tillage to doe: or elſe doe this, follow the example of a Gentleman that made a great quantitie of ſoile, by the fodering of all his Cattell vpon a peece of exceeding ranke ground about an Acre, which being very good and reſtie Land neere his houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:8"/>he plowed vp in the end of Aprill, when his Cattell went to graſſe, and with two or three plowings ſo mixed the reſtie ranke ground with the doung and ſo fodder of his cattell, that he had ten loade for one of very good ſoile, (to the fatting of other grounds) then otherwiſe he ſhould haue had; and alſo there is much dounge to be made with Ferne in places where it is neere: many good Husbands do prouide great ſtore in ſummer, that in win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter will ſerue for cattell to ſit drie vpon, and make great ſtore of ſoile, with little coſt, hauing now ſo much leiſure in this ſmall Tillage. By theſe and diuers other good meanes very common and eaſie, when men haue little plowing, they may ſo inrich their land, that they ſhall not neede to doubt of a better increaſe (by Gods helpe) ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to pay the charge of ſetting liberally, with three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold increaſe at Harueſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Then you may fall into another inconueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that I warned you of in my booke, that is, to make your land too ranke, and then your Corne will ledge, and euery ſtalke will be ſlender and long, euery eare will be heauier and longer than ordinarie, and ſo the Corne will fall downe and ledge, and cometo little good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>This inconuenience will eaſilie be hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped. Wee had firſt neede to helpe our barren land, and make it hartie, and then for falling and ledging I will ſet it thin enough, as the qualitie of the ground requireth: for it is the thicke ſowing of ranke land vpon euill tillage that cauſeth Corne to ledge.<note place="margin">Note.</note> If the land be rich and the yeere wet, the Corne ranke, and the weedes many; then (as you ſay) it is like to ledge: few poore men in England complaine their land is too rich, or deſire their Corne more thin, for then their purſes would be more emptie. I could eaſilie teach them ſuch tricks as well as you with all
<pb facs="tcp:13488:9"/>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſon and experience teacheth and proueth, that the ſtraw will be bigger and much ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note>your cunning: and as for the length and ſlendernes of the ſtraw, I doubt not but it will be fit to beare the heauie eares, which God ſend me, and take you the light if you like them better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Your reaſons may proue good for ſowing, but for ſetting, you will be ſet a ground preſentlie. For where will you get people enow to ſet a Seaſon fit for a Teeme to be kept on? All the labourers in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie will ſcant ſerue you, and fiue or ſixe ſuch as you would be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I wonder what you meane to talke ſtill ſo idlie, as though it were fit for me or any man, to ſet our whole ſeaſons, when we haue laide all our ſoile, and beſtowed all our labour, tillage, and coſt, vpon the third part onely, to the intent to make that ſo hartie and rich, that by all reaſon, common experience, and Gods bleſſing, it may yeeld as much and more increaſe than the whole would haue done. Neither am I tied by any neceſſitie (that I know of) to ſet all my third part, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe I may doe it conuenientlie in all reſpects: <note place="margin">Note well.</note>for when I haue thus plowed my land and made it readie to ſet, I may ſowe thereof what I will if I lacke ſetters, and it is likelie to beare three times as much, being thus well handled; as other poore barren land ſo miſuſed for lacke of ſuch good Husbandrie. But now for ſetting of ten Acres of Wheate or Rie, or other graine, being the third part of moſt mens Seaſon, why ſhould I not finde people enow to ſet them, ſeeing you confeſſe that threeſcore la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers, and twentie women and children, will digge and ſet thirtie Acres in ſeuen weekes? Why good ſir, if I be at the charge, and can dreſſe my land with my Plough my ſelfe, what haue I to doe with your threeſcore labourers that ſhould haue been imployed in your digging: I will
<pb facs="tcp:13488:9"/>ſpare them all for you, ſeeing you will needes haue ſo many Acres digged, for you might as well haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode Maſter <hi>Plat,</hi> the author of the firſt booke, that he meant not to haue the whole number of euery mans ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be digged, when he propoſed that three Acres might beare as much as thirtie: And although I am of your opinion, this will ſeldome proue true in action, yet cannot you nor the beſt Scholler in England diſproue the principles that he grounds his proportion vpon, for he addes diuers approued examples in practiſe to proue his arguments. And for your twentie women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, poore people, I am ſorrie; for the moſt of them may ſtill want worke, and liue a ſtaruing kinde of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable life, for by your perſwaſions they ſhould earne iuſt nothing; and ſo none of the poore by this meanes ſet to worke in your Husbandrie. Well, yet I will propoſe leſſe worke by the third part in my Husbandrie, and ſo will haue but the third part of your women and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;<note place="margin">Note.</note> which being but ſeuen, will ſet my ten Acres in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen weekes, whileſt your threeſcore diggers and twentie women and children be digging and ſetting your thirtie Acres in the ſame time by your owne account: and by Gods helpe, if this third part of the land be imployed, we ſhall haue worke ſufficient for all our poore people, and poore people enow for all our worke. I will therefore ſpare you foure or fiue of thoſe ſeuen poore people for a ſupplie to your companie, leaſt any ſhould happen to faile in ſome hot skirmiſh, and then I ſhall onely be troubled with ſome two or three of your poore people, or ſome lame Souldier; <note place="margin">Prouiſion for lame and mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Souldiers</note>he will ſerue my turne though he want a legge or an arme: and ſo let vs recken the charge of three poore women and children, which will be hired for eighteene pence a day at moſt, which is but nine ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb facs="tcp:13488:10"/>
                  <note place="margin">Charges of ſetting.</note>a weeke, and for ſeuen weekes is three poundes three ſhillings for the wages of thoſe poore people, vnto whom I will ioyne our two plow-folkes; for away goe our Teemes to reſt and gather fleſh againſt winter, our Wiues will ſpare one of their maides, and many of vs haue two or three children, and our ſelues for ouer-ſeers of the worke, all theſe are aboue nine perſons for your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and all their charges is but three poundes three ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings more than ordinarie;<note place="margin">Ten Acres as ſoone plowed and ſet with ſeuen people, as thirtie dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and ſet with ſoure ſcore.</note> and ſo you ſee that two or three poore people at moſt with our owne familie, ſhall be as well able to ſet our ten Acres in ſeuen weekes, as your foureſcore men, women and children ſhall digge and ſet thirtie Acres in the very ſame time. But if you thinke that Wheate or Rie will be ſet in the beginning of March in rich land, as you ſay in your booke (and truly I am of your opinion) and the rather, becauſe you affirme that the beſt croppe of Corne that euer you ſaw, was a ſommer croppe of Wheate vpon a rich ground: now it will be a great commoditie if we may ſtay to ſet our richeſt land vntill after Chriſtide: for by ſome meanes or other, we may by that time make ſome of our land better than other, and the nature of ſome land of it ſelfe is much better than other; then will we ſet our pooreſt land firſt, and begin about the middle of September, or neere thereupon, euery Countrie and place, as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the land requireth, and ſo continue ſetting in the faireſt weather, vntill the middle of December or there abouts; ſo then we ſhall haue ſome thirteene weeks at leaſt before Chriſtide, and ſome ſeuen weekes after, before March.<note place="margin">It is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine that this late ſetting or ſowing being in very good ground, is the beſt to auoide the Mildew and the ſmut.</note> Thus a poore Farmer may well ſet ten Acres in twentie weekes with his owne familie, hauing wife and children as moſt haue, and doe it all by leaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>I muſt needes confeſſe, that your experience
<pb facs="tcp:13488:10"/>
                  <note place="margin">Your miſlike or writing, will not hinder, if it proue profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</note>hath taught you to ſay more in this matter than I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of it before. But yet ſeeing you looke for no more increaſe than ſixe or eight quarters vpon an Acre, it is not the admirable arte the firſt booke ſpeakes of (which made me miſlike and write as I did) for many men in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers places haue had the like increaſe; neither doe I yet perceiue how the charges of ſetting will be anſwered, nor any matter worthie ſo great account as you make of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>What you ſee I know not, or what the cauſe ſhould be I cannot tell, that ſo many men ſhould be ſo blinde or ſo vnwilling to ſee how to doe themſelues and their neighbours ſo much good: but I feare me it is the iuſt puniſhment of God vpon vs the ſinfull people of this good Land, that we hauing ſo great plentie of all good things, do conſume with gluttonie and with drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe ſo great bleſſings of God alreadie beſtowed vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs:<note place="margin">A caueat for gluttons and drunkards.</note> and if we ſhould by this meanes or any other, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a greater aboundance than yet we haue receiued, it is to be feared that the Lord that ſeeth how wickedlie we would conſume it, will not permit ſuch an vnthankfull people to receiue ſo exceeding great a benefit, but euen by our owne frowardnes will quite ouerthrow it.<note place="margin">Take heede of murmuring and vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, ioyned with froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> But yet let vs ſee if we can poſſiblie be brought to diſcerne any thing worthie account in this noueltie, as you tearme it: And for example, ſay that thirtie Acres by Rodde, will require three buſhels of ſeede <hi>Winchester</hi> meaſure to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Acre,<note place="margin">In ſome part of Eſſex their land requireth leſſe ſeede, well obſerued by ſome good Husbands.</note> (for ſo you ſay it will) and ſo in moſt land it doth, which is eleuen quarters and two buſhels of ſeede to thirtie Acres: What is the vſuall increaſe vpon an Acre in the common fields barren land?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>The increaſe of an Acre of ſuch barren land, commonly is not aboue two quarters one yeere with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:11"/>and one Acre with another, and when they ſo doe, there neede be no dearth in England; for where one hath aboue, three hath not ſo much: and therefore you will hardlie approue that your ſetting will be to any great purpoſe in thoſe common fields, barren Land.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The beſt ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Corne is in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fields, barren land, when by theſe inſtructions it is ſo amended.</note>Verie well ſir, I am glad you haue decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red your conceite in this poynt, and euen for thoſe bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Countries and barren common fields, doe I auowe this Husbandrie to be moſt profitable, and for their ſakes onlie and altogether doe I take all this paines, and vſe ſo manie perſwaſions againſt ſo many fond obiections, as you and moſt men vſe againſt this good Husbandrie of Corne ſetting, and not for thoſe that are occupiers of rich land, either by nature or ſo made by ſoile. Their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe is plentifull alreadie, and therefore I thinke it no great worke of charitie to beſtow much labour vpon ſuch rich men, as commonlie with good Husbandrie vſe ſuch rich land: but I ſpeake and write for poore men, and deſire to make their poore land and them the richer by this good Husbandrie, which I will maintaine vpon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall tearmes or by practiſe, with any Husbandman in England, of what countrie or ſhire ſo euer he be or dwell in. <note place="margin">Note well.</note>And now to our purpoſe again, and I pray you marke well what I ſay, you confeſſe (as the truth is) that an Acre by the Rodde will beare but two quarters commonlie one yeere with another, which is but threeſcore quarters for thirtie Acres, and that ſuch an Acre will require three buſhels to ſowe it, which is for thirtie Acres eleuen quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and two buſhels of ſeede, as aforeſaide; ſo then take your eleuen quarters two buſhels of ſeede ſowed at ſeede time, out of threeſcore quarters reaped at harueſt, there will remaine fortie eight quarters and ſixe buſhels in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by this computation: then come to our ten Acres
<pb facs="tcp:13488:11"/>of like meaſure, which will be ſet with fiue buſhels, what may we looke for euerie yeere vpon an Acre ſet with halfe a buſhell? by Gods bleſſing we are as likelie to haue ſixe or ſeuen quarters vpon an Acre that is well dunged, tilled, the ſeede choiſelie picked, and the land orderlie ſet, as other haue had vpon an Acre ſowne, which is vpon ten Acres threeſcore and ten quarters: And what is then our increaſe of theſe ten Acres, if you take fiue buſhels of ſeede ſet at ſeede time, out of threeſcore and ten quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters reaped at harueſt, there will remaine ſome threeſcore and nine quarters and three buſhels increaſe; ſo it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that our increaſe by ſetting of ten Acres with fiue buſhels, is more then by ſowing of thirtie Acres with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuen quarters and two buſhels, by ſome twenty quarters and fiue buſhels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>Say that all this doe follow, as you would haue it, and truly I cannot deny but it may; yet the charge of ſetting and the trouble will be ſo great, that it will not be worth the practiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, it is manifeſtlie proued, that two or three poore people with the ordinarie familie of all men that ſowe thirtie Acres to a ſeaſon, may ſet ten Acres, and that the wages of thoſe poore people for ſetting time, was but three poundes three ſhillings at ſixe pence a day: and for that charge, you do ſaue twentie Acres of land at fiue ſhillings an Acre, fiue poundes; and the Plowing of that land three plowings to euery Acre before you ſowe it, which is threeſcore plowings at two ſhillings euerie time, is ſixe poundes: then you ſaue ſome twentie quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and fiue buſhels of Corne as aforeſaid, worth in moſt yeeres twenty ſhillings a quarter, comes to twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie poundes twelue ſhillings ſixe pence. So by this recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which in truth and ſubſtance cannot be denied,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:12"/>you will ſaue ſome one and thirtie poundes twelue ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings ſixe pence. And although I doe priſe the twentie Acres ſo ſpared as aforeſaid, at fiue ſhillings an Acre (as it were to be let out for rent) yet I rather thinke that any good Husband that ſo ſpareth twentie Acres to reſt from his principall ſeaſons or Wheate, Rie, or Barlie, will ſowe (after the olde faſhion if it pleaſe him) ſome ſixe, eight, or ten Acres with Peaſe, Beanes, Bucke, otherwiſe called french Wheate, or with Oates vpon one earth or Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, whereby he may haue great ſtore of ſtrawe for his Cattell, meate for his wiues Hens, and prouender for his Horſe, ouer and beſides ſo much increaſe and profite of thoſe ſixe, eight or ten Acres, as ſhall defraie all the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie charge of ſetting with aduantage. And becauſe I haue heard this kinde of complaint often; and many men doubt their neighbours and their own ſeruants will not meddle with ſuch a pidling troubleſome worke, whoſe frowardnes no doubt will doe much hurt: I wiſh any ſuch that dwell amongſt ſuch neighbours, or haue ſuch ſeruants (as indeed I thinke many haue) to ſell ſome three or foure quarters of their ſeede corne, that before was ſpared, and allow double their wages to ſtraungers, and I will aſſure them workmen plentie to doe ſo eaſie and cleane a worke. And yet then the charge will be but ſixe pound ſixe ſhillings: which taken out of the former profits, there will remaine ſome twentie fiue pound ſixe ſhillings ſixe pence, which will helpe a poore Farmer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the payment of his rent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scholler.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">This obiection is none of your owne Maſter Scholler, you had helpe of a Lawyer.</note>Your compariſon betweene tenne acres paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing well husbanded and made rich, and then ſet, and thirtie acres of barren land ſowed, no doubt will bee a matter of great difference, and therefore I wiſh to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of all men. But what ſay you to good land, either
<pb facs="tcp:13488:12"/>by nature or helpe of ſoyle, that will vſually beare fiue or ſixe quarters vpon an acre? and if your ſetting will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to no more increaſe, then after a man hath laid all his coſt vpon ſo ſmall quantitie of land, and made it ſo good, he will ſow it, and ſaue the charge of ſetting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ploughman.</speaker>
               <p>If this booke do but perſwade our coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen, that occupie much barren land, to ſow but the third part or halfe their land, which they were wont to worke out of heart, with their poore cattell and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, I ſhall not onely thinke my labour happely beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed in writing, but all the poore people may thank God as much for the printing of it, as for any booke ſet foorth in our time, (for a matter of this qualitie) and which is of no ſmall importance for the common-wealth of this land. But yet I muſt not yeeld that plowing and ſowing will be of like profit for the common-wealth, as plowing and ſetting, ſeeing the ſame will be done yet with much leſſe charge, comparing tenne acres of the beſt land ſet, with other tenne as good ſowed, which I will prooue by example and tried experience: and firſt it is wel knowne by often triall, that leſſe then halfe a buſhel of very choiſe ſeede wheate, will ſet as much land as three buſhels will ſowe. So that whereas ten or twelue great Acres of land will require ſome three or foure quarters to ſowe them; the ſame land may be ſet with ſixe or ſeuen buſhels at the moſt, for there will be faued ſome three quarters of the beſt ſeede Corne euery yeere, which is now worth fortie ſhillings a quarter, and commeth to ſixe poundes, and exceedeth the extraordinarie charge of ſetting aforeſaid by much,<note place="margin">Fiue or ſixe thouſand quarters of Graine ſaued euery yeare by Corne ſetting, all obiections anſwered.</note> and will amount to the ſauing of ſome three hundred thouſand quarters of the beſt Wheate and Rie growing in this Land: and much more in Barlie, Peaſe, and Beanes, and ſo of all ſorts of graine: I thinke it would
<pb facs="tcp:13488:13"/>ſaue aboue fiue or ſixe hundred thouſand quarters euery yeere in her Maieſties Dominions. And yet giue mee leaue to tell you Gentleman, that I dare confidently a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uow (ſeeing both reaſon doth teach and experience doth proue) that an Acre orderly ſet, will yeeld more increaſe by ſome three quarters, than an Acre ſowne: which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe at Harueſt being added to the other three quarters ſaued at ſeede time, commeth to ſome ſixe quarters of Corne at fortie ſhillings a quarter, twelue pound, as it is now worth, in many Countries, which will defray the charges of ſetting double, though your Plowmen follow their Teemes &amp; giue vs no help. And yet this I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that in time of great plentie, when Corne is at a low price, and where chargeable ſeruants or labourers dwell,<note place="margin">Chargeable ſeruants and ill workemen, a great hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to all good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandire.</note> that will not ſerue or worke vnder fiue pound and a fuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an doublet; or in ſuch places where their land and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are ſo rich: with ſuch times, places and perſons, this poore booke, or rather booke for the poore, hath yet little to ſay, vntil ſuch time as they be brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; that after great plentie may follow as great ſcarſitie, the wealthieſt Corne-maſter and ſtouteſt labourer or ſeruant, may in time become like one of their pooreſt neighbours. Great men in this and all ages haue been ſubiect to their fall.<note place="margin">Laſie vſurie, a capitall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandrie, lewes onely did vſe it in England, about the raigne of King Richard the firſt, anno 1189. <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.1. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> was accounted as rich in his time, as the greateſt Corne-maſter or the wealthieſt Vſurer that liues in our time: yet the Lord made an example of his ſeruant <hi>Iob</hi> to all poſteritie, albeit hee was <hi>an vpright and iuſt man, one that feared God and eſchued euil. If vengeance begin at the houſe of God, where ſhall the wicked and vngodly appeare.</hi> I write not this againſt good minded men, whom it hath pleaſed God to bleſſe with plentie of Corne, and yet loue their brethren and poore neighbours: ſome ſuch good men no doubt haue been and yet are in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:13"/>who may be accounted patterns for others to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, or patrons, that is, fathers to their Countrie, by ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring vp Corne in the time of plentie, with purpoſe to bring it forth in ſcarcitie, to ſell it at a lower rate for the good of the poore. Such good men no doubt are to be praiſed with gracious <hi>Ioſeph,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the people prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth Gods wrath.</note> who by laying vp of Corne in the time of plenty, preſerued not only the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Aegypt, but alſo the whole Church of God, then viſible on earth, for which cauſe his induſtrie is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded and commended for the inſtruction of all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. And by the way, I wiſh all murmuring people to conſider what it is to grudge and repine againſt Gods works, and to be more aduiſed how they ſpeake againſt good Magiſtrates and ſuch good men, as carefullie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the publike weale of the Land. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.2. <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.13.</note>Furthermore, that it may yet appeare more manifeſtly, that plowing and ſetting of Corne is euery way much more profitable and leſſe chargeable than plowing and ſowing, and that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Farmer may eaſilie ſet the third part of his land with his owne familie, and two or three of the pooreſt people only at ſetting time (whereby he may yet haue more lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to practiſe and performe euerie complement that ſhall be likelie to further his increaſe) let him Tyll but the third part of his land, as of thirtie Acres ten, and ſo whereas he was wont to giue his thirtie Acres vpon a ſommer fallow, ſome foure or fiue plowings (as ſome grounds will require) and as moſt good Husbands doe: for thereby they doe kill the weedes, which of all things I would all men ſhould moſt ſpeciallie regard: So then thirtie Acres hauing at leaſt foure plowings, amounteth to an hundred and twentie daies worke at the leaſt; and ten Acres hauing fiue plowings euerie Acre, which is but fiftie daies worke at the moſt: ſo here is threeſcore and
<pb facs="tcp:13488:14"/>ten daies worke ſpared in your winter ſeaſon for Wheate or Rie, and as much for Barlie, which being in all one hundred and twentie daies worke or there about, is very neere the third part of the whole yeere ſpared for your Plowes and Teemes,<note place="margin">The third part of the yeere ſpared from plowing, by ſetting of corne, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forget not therein to forue God.</note> which I wiſh ſhould be otherwiſe imployed to ſome good worke, as no doubt but euerie good Husband will finde worke enough for them to do. But yet let them beſtowe ſome part of this time ſo well gained, a little to ſerue God in prayer morning and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, either in their priuat families, or with a diligent Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter (they that dwel neere the Church) one halfe houre in a morning or euening, or both: if they haue any thing to doe at Church with God, or with their neighbours, it will be a good meeting place if it be done to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. It is a ſmall portion of ſo many daies ſpared, and no doubt but God will the rather bleſſe the increaſe of ſuch as will ſerue him, according as he hath promiſed; and as the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Paul</hi> planteth, <hi>Apollo</hi> watereth, but it is the Lord, no doubt, that giueth the increaſe, as well in temporall as in ſpirituall bleſſings.<note place="margin">Beware of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme.</note> Thus we all muſt beleeue, and ſo I hope we doe, vnleſſe there be any of ſo deſperate and curſed opinion, that thinks there is no God to bleſſe and helpe their increaſe, which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid that her Maieſties dominions ſhould beare any ſuch deteſtable and curſed imps and lims of Sathan to reſt on this earth, that ſhould ſo much as giue any cauſe of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſuch abomination: ſo as many as doe ſo well begin the day with the ſeruice of God, may cheerefullie expect from the Almightie a bleſſing vpon their labours: who promiſeth to bleſſe the worke of our hands if we feare him. And to proceede in this argument yet a little further in our Husbandrie, which no doubt may be yet exceeding lie furthered diuers waies in this time ſo well
<pb facs="tcp:13488:14"/>gained: as firſt to make great choiſe of our Seede corne: for as Maſter <hi>Plat</hi> well ſaith, euerie corne that is within the eare is not apt to grow, for God hath created ſome of them for the food of liuing creatures, and ſome for ſeed. <note place="margin">The choiſe of the ſeede, the killing of the weede, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of the land, and time ſo well gained, to doe all this and ſerue God too, is like to bring a good increaſe.</note>There be in euerie eare certaine abortiue or baſtardlie cornes ſmall and whinderlings, which will hardlie grow, and are vnprofitable for any good increaſe: but there are other cornes which are bigger and fairer then the reſt, which (no doubt) God by nature hath ordained for good and great increaſe: and therefore ſeeing you haue ſo much leiſure, you may ſpend more time in picking your Seede, corne after corne, if you thinke good. <note place="margin">The beſt way to make choiſe of your ſeede.</note>But indeed the beſt way and moſt ſpeedie is to put the corne into a tub of water, and ſo the moſt heauie corne will ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſinke to the bottome, and the lighteſt (with other ſeedes which were wont to be ſowen) you may take pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentlie away: for els in a ſmall time the lighter will alſo ſinke, by taking water to make it heauie alſo. But you muſt doe this but a little before you intend to ſow it, and in doing whereof you may helpe your Seed corne verie much, as it were with a dunging, as I my ſelfe haue done my Seede barlie. When the yeere hath prooued drie at Barlie ſeed time, I haue cauſed certaine wotting fattes or tubs, vſed for Malting, to be filled with water, and cauſed Cow dung and Pigeon dung to be put into the ſame wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſtirring it together, and it hath ſtood a day or two, but the longer the better, with often ſtirring it. Then haue I let or powred out the ſame water from the dung, and put it into other cleane veſſels: and then I put in my Seede all day and all night, and the next day tooke it out and laid it vpon a floore to dry it fit to handle, and caſt abroad by ſowing. And trulie that Barlie hath ſhot an eare as ſoone as other that was ſowen ſome fourteene daies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:13488:15"/>it. Whereof (in my opinion) one great commoditie dooth follow, in that the corne (ſpeciallie Barlie) at that time of the yeere commeth away ſo ſpeedelie, that it out groweth all the weedes, who are the chiefe and deadlie enemies to all corne. Thus the corne may flouriſh and be maſter of the field, like a braue Captaine: for ſo no doubt hee getteth better roote to begin the world with, and more heart to continue and bring foorth increaſe more aboundantlie, when it hath at firſt gotten the ſtart and vpper hand of his mortall enemies. <note place="margin">One hundred and twentie daies yet ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for good Husbands, to inrich their land and themſelues.</note>This picking and watring worke is fitteſt to be performed by the good wife, and her maides, and children at home, and our hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twentie daies that wee ſpared from plowing, as aforeſaid, yet giueth more time to the good man and his Ploughmen with their Teemes to fetch Marle of Chalk, or of any other kind of ſoile, fit for the condition of their land, if it be poſſible to be had, as no doubt it is in moſt places, though in ſome they may happen to goe farre for it: but in ſixe or ſeuen weekes (part of the foreſaid time) a Teeme will carrie much, though it be farre to fetch. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo thoſe that haue ſower barren colde grounds, may in this time all by leiſure, follow the example of the Corniſh and Deuonſhire men, that beate and burne their land, which no doubt is an excellent peece of good Husbandrie, and now vſed by good Husbands in manie places of England and Wales. <note place="margin">A commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wall and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uonſhire.</note>And whereof Cornewall and Deuon hath ſo taſted the benefit, that whereas of late time Cornewall was wont to haue moſt of their bread-corne by ſea from other countries, now by this meanes they haue great plentie to ſpare, and ſend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer much by ſea into other countries. There will be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other profitable workes found out by manie good Husbands to keepe their people and Teemes at worke,
<pb facs="tcp:13488:15"/>
                  <note place="margin">The Plow and the Spade ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good fri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>eds, &amp; allow each others worke for ſetting, as the place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth.</note>if it pleaſe them, and ſuch as haue a better minde to vſe the Spade to ſet their Corne: and ſo by experience ſhall finde much better increaſe, which I will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, but it may be ſo; nor diſcommend the induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous inuention and practiſe of the Spade, and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie for ſetting of poore people to worke, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede is a matter of great regard, which by no meanes I would hinder: for as in this action by ſetting of Corne, the chiefe and principall reſpect is the ſauing of ſuch a goodlie deale of Seede Corne yeerelie ſo fondlie caſt away, as before is ſhewed; ſo ſpeciallie by ſetting of Corne the pooreſt and moſt miſerable people, that can otherwiſe earne little or nothing, ſhall now be ſet to worke, becauſe they are beſt cheape to be hired, and are as well able to performe this worke as the luſtie labourers, that ſometime in ſome countries no reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable wages will intertaine them:<note place="margin">Middleſex, Kent, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces neere the mightie citie of London.</note> theſe are fit for rich men, and to be imployed in rich land, where the owners may haue rich crops to pay ſuch great wages to ſuch proud labourers and ſeruants, that will ſerue and worke where they liſt, and haue what wages they liſt, and then doe what they liſt, make what lawes and ſtatutes her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, her Councell and the Parliament can deuiſe: I meane ſuch ſeruants as intend not to ſerue their maſters faithfullie for their maſters profit, but for their owne, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom there are manie theeues, which ſome Gentlemen, Farmers and other, with their wiues and children haue dearely paid for, to their great and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table loſſe and hindrance. This proud kinde of ſlouens and ſluts, which ſome maſters haue and doe keepe from the halter, haue no need to be pitied, but rather to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. <note place="margin">A reward for faithfull and good ſeruants.</note>And ſuch maſters whom it pleaſeth God to bleſſe with a good ſeruant, let him be accompted as a precious
<pb facs="tcp:13488:16"/>iewell, and vſed with due reſpect, pay him his wages tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and leaue him not a poore man: It is the Lord the great Maſter his commaundement by the wiſe <hi>Salomon,</hi> as you may reade in his Prouerbes. As touching the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments to bee employed about ſetting of Corne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I might leaue euerie man to his owne inuention, or referre them to Maſter <hi>Plats</hi> booke, whoſe inſtructions in many things I doe commend: yet becauſe it may be that all men haue not that booke, and deſire ſome inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, therefore I will recite an example of his, which he beſt commendeth, which is a boord of three foote in length, or thereabouts, and twelue or tenne inches in breadth, hauing diuers holes bored therein, according to ſuch diſtance as euerie particular man dooth beſt fanſie, through each of which holes a woodden dipper or pin to be thruſt into the ground, being of the bignes of ones finger, and of three or foure inches in length, hauing a ſhoulder or croſſe-pin to keepe one ſelfe ſame certaintie in the depth of each hole. Now my inuention is to haue two boords of ſome two foote broad euerie where, and in the middle a ſtaffe or handle ſet faſt to remoue them: or if any doe like better to haue them one foote broad, and two or three foot long, and in euerie of thoſe boords one or two ſtaues or handles, of ſome two foote high ſet faſt to remooue them, and alſo to leaue vpon for their worſhips eaſe: but for this matter of making of holes, I muſt ſay with you maſter Scholler, <hi>I profeſſe to preſſe this argument no further, being no part of my profeſsion,</hi> but leaue it to them that ſhall vſe and practiſe this inuention. Only this I doe aduiſe that euerie man doe well conſider the qualitie of his owne ground, if it bee exceeding ranke, foure or fiue inches diſtance; but moſt commonly three or foure inches is likely to be moſt fit, and two or three
<pb facs="tcp:13488:16"/>inches deepe, as the ground is heauie or light. And perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture the clods may ſometime hinder: for which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this boorde and this handle or two be verie fit to thruſt downe the clods. Theſe boords are to be directed by a line, to keepe a ſtreight courſe in ſetting, hauing al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies a Rake with thicke teeth and a broad head, which at one pull will ſufficiently fill all the holes. And for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, to ſuch as are verie ſimple, it is thought good to ſet downe the order of making of the holes in euerie boord, as the ſame holes ſhall be of diſtance more or leſſe: as if your boord be tenne inches broad and three foote long, and your holes fiue inches diſtance, there muſt bee two rowes of holes and feuen holes in a row, and at euery end and fide there muſt be two inches and more left, and for euery ſcantling or diſtance, whether it be three, foure, or fiue inches, leaue alwaies the outſide and the ends halfe the diſtance or leſſe in euerie boord, and ſo it will make a true continuance of one ſcantling throughout all the worke. But if this labour by writing and printing be loſt in the behalfe of plowing and ſetting, and that men ſhuld continue ſo wilfullie blind to deſpiſe Gods bleſſings vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themſelues, their poore neighbours, and the whole Common-wealth: yet it is to be wiſhed that where men are ſo obſtinatelie addicted to old cuſtome, they would yet follow the olde prouerbe, which ſaith, <hi>A little land well tild, a little houſe well fild, and a little wife well wild,</hi> no doubt but his little land would be as profitable for his purſe, as his little good wife comfortable to his minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Thus I draw to an end, deſiring the reader to take ſome view of ſuch great benefits as this action of plowing and ſetting may (by Gods mercie) bring to this our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. And I leaue the ſucceſſe to Gods good bleſsing. And firſt (here I ſay) the plowing taketh away the laborious
<pb facs="tcp:13488:17"/>and chargeable worke of the Spade, which made ſetting of corne ſeeme vnprofitable, and vnpoſſible to haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borers and people ſufficient to dreſſe and ſet fiftie Acres, of three thouſand in a Pariſh, as the aduerſe booke ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. This now by plowing and ſetting is prooued that euerie third Acre may be ſet in all places throughout her Maieſties Dominions. Secondly, it prooueth plowing and ſetting to be leſſe chargeable then plowing and ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <note place="margin">Prouiſion for lame ſouldiers and poore children. This benefit is not lightly to be reſpected.</note>Thirdly, wee haue prooued that this may be done by the ordinarie familie of moſt men, with ſome helpe of two or three of his pooreſt neighbours, old men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, poore children, lame and diſtreſſed ſouldiers, that now can haue no worke for their liuing. Fourthly, I ſay this, theſe poore people (that indeede ought to bee kept from a ſtaruing kinde of life in ſo plentifull a Countrie as England is, by the wealthie inhabitants of euerie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, to whom now they are both chargeable and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous) by this good meanes they may be kept from hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, cold, nakednes, and idlenes, breeding monſtrous vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces againſt God, her Maieſtie, and this preſent happie State; deſeruing whipping and hanging, to the ſpoile of their bodies, &amp; perill of their ſoules. Fiftly, it ſaueth great abundance of the beſt corne, growing within her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions, which now is yeerly caſt away and loſt by ſowing, or rather burying it too deepe vnder furrow, or lying too ſhallow aboue furrow, for Crowes and Mice and other vermine to deuoure from the poore people. Sixtly, it ſpareth two parts of the land, that is, of thirtie Acres twentie may be ſpared to lie and reſt to gather hart for a while, and after when it is plowed againe it will bring forth increaſe of corne abundantly, as all m<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e know. Seuenthly, it will increaſe great ſtore of paſture in the common fields, to the reliefe of all cattell, and whereby
<pb facs="tcp:13488:17"/>
               <note place="margin">Two hundred paſture ſheepe well fed, will dung a fould better then three hundred poore ſheepe hungerly kept</note>there may be kept both greater number and better ſheep both for growth, wooll and ſoundnes, that by theſe meanes, being plentifullie fed, will inlarge the poore mans fould, and alſo they wil dung his land much better, to the like increaſe of corne in greater abundance. Eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it will ſaue great quantities of Hey and Corne for horſemeate, which now is ſpent vpon poore working cattell tired to death, with great ſtore of worke vpon much tillage of barren land: ſo that when by this meanes great quantities of graſſe and hey is ſaued from working cattell, then greater ſtore maybe reſerued to the fatting of cattell; ſo that Gentlemen, Farmers, and other houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders may feede many of their owne Oxen, Cowes and Sheepe fat, and need not go ſo often to the Butchers, and then their Kine will giue much more milke to make Butter and Cheeſe, when they are much better fed with graſſe and hey plentifullie: and of theſe it will come to paſſe that their bacon Hogges ſhall be fed fat with their whey of their Kine, and with the corne that the working cattell were wont to eate vp, and then ſhall thoſe houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders haue leſſe neede of the Markets for their houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold prouiſion, which will be a meanes to bring downe the price of all fleſh (fit to be eaten) and of white meate, that the poore Artificers and labourers may eate their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals better cheape. Ninthly, it wil be a notable meanes to ouerthrow the wicked depopulation of the Lordes people, her Maieſties louing ſubiects, who haue bin moſt lamentably driuen out of their habitations, and diuers townes and villages, ouerthrowne by incloſures, which yet continue, and rather will increaſe, notwithſtanding the great care and order taken by her Maieſtie, and the great officers of her Kingdomes in the high Court of Parliament, as appeareth by an act made of purpoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:13488:18"/>
               <note place="margin">Setting of Corne good for Seafaring men, let them praiſe God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</note>the ſame. Tenthly, it will breede and ſaue ſuch plentie of corne in England, by Gods helpe, that we may ſpare great quantities to be tranſported without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice, but rather great good to all our Engliſh nation of all ſorts, as well poore as rich, to the great increaſe of the treaſurie of this Realme, the maintenance of our Engliſh Nauie, Shipping and Marriners, with prouiſion of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals for her Maieſties ſouldiers and Armies, by Sea and by Land, to the feare and terror of all forreine enemies.</p>
            <p>Theſe and many other excellent benefits (no doubt) would follow this good kinde of Husbandrie, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth a more learned handling then I can ſay, or doe profeſſe to be in me. If any man doe thinke this worke to be needleſſe, for that there is alreadie ſufficiently written in former bookes: I anſwere, that to my knowledge there is none that hath hitherto written of the plowing and ſetting of Corne; neither doe I perceiue the people ſo inſtructed, but rather moſt ignorant, and great numbers doe vtterly proteſt againſt the practiſe, as an idle noueltie, being lately diſcouraged by this Pamphlet, called <hi>God ſpeede the Plough.</hi> Now the Almightie bleſſe all good husbands in Husbandrie, and graunt a bleſſing to this mine endeuour, to his glorie, the honour of our Prince, the comfort of the poore, and the generall good of all the Land.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="comparison">
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:18"/>
            <head>A COMPARISON BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TWEENE PLOWING AND SOWING OF THREE ACRES of land, after the old faſhion, and plowing and ſetting of one Acre after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner declared in this Booke.</head>
            <head type="sub">And firſt for the Charge.</head>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Computa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for poore Farmers that pay great rents.</note>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE rent of three Acres in moſt places is worth ſome fiue ſhillings an Acre. The land, according to the vſe of the common fields, doth lie ſommer fallow the firſt yeere, and beareth Corne the other, and ſo the Farmer payeth two yeeres rent before hee hath his crop, which rent com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to thirtie ſhillings.</p>
            <p>The plowing of theſe, if it bee well done, and as moſt grounds require, euery Acre foure times, which is twelue plowings, at two ſhillings euery time commeth to foure and twentie ſhillings.</p>
            <p>The dunging of theſe three Acres with ſome twelue or fourteene loade vpon euery Acre, and is for three A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres ſome fortie loade, at ſixe pence a loade, ſpread vpon the land, amounteth to twentie ſhillings.</p>
            <p>The ſeede that will ſow it is vſually two buſhels and a halfe of Wheate or Rye for euery Acre, which is ſeuen buſhels and a halfe, at foure ſhillings the buſhel, commeth to thirtie ſhillings.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13488:19"/>
            <p>The weeding, reaping, and other charges in two yeers, though vncertaine, yet for example ten ſhillings. Thus two yeeres rent and charges commeth to fiue pound fourteene ſhillings.</p>
            <p>The vſuall increaſe in the common fields barren land, hauing ſo little help with dung, is but two quarters vpon an Acre: but allow twentie buſhels to ſtop a wranglers mouth, which is for three Acres ſeuen quarters and a halfe, rated at foure ſhillings a buſhell, thirtie two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings the quarter, commeth to twelue poundes. Out of which if you take the charge aforeſaid, there remaineth to the Farmer for his ſtock, ſixe pound ſixe ſhillings. And ſo for euery one of thoſe Acres, allowing ſo good increaſe and ſo great a price, the profit is two and fortie ſhillings.</p>
            <p>Then let vs ſee what profit one Acre, being well plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, well dunged, and orderly ſet, will yeeld, and ſo for the charge of one Acre. The rent of one Acre, at the price a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, which was fiue ſhillings an Acre, for two yeeres ten ſhillings. The plowing fiue times for this one Acre, if neede be, ten ſhillings. The dunging with fortie loade vpon this Acre at ſixe pence a loade, twentie ſhillings. The ſeede to ſet this one Acre, halfe a buſhell, two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. The ſetting of this Acre, one man at eight pence a day, and ſome foure poore people at foure pence a day, will ſet this Acre in ſome ſixe daies, and all their wages is twelue ſhillings. The weeding, reaping, and other char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, three ſhillings foure pence. The ſumme of the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges commeth to ſeuen and fiftie ſhillings foure pence.</p>
            <p>This Acre ſo wel tilled, with three times as much dung as any one of the other, with excellent ſeede and orderly ſet, although we cannot promiſe thirtie or twentie quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, yet we may haue ſeuen or eight quarters vpon an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre, which is vſuall vpon very good land, which being ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at foure ſhillings, as the other, commeth to twelue pound ſixteene ſhillings. Out of which alſo if you take the charge, which is fiftie ſeuen ſhillings foure pence, there will remaine nine pound eighteene ſhillings eight pence. And ſo this one Acre exceedeth the other three in profits, with halfe the ſtock, the ſumme of three pound twelue ſhillings eight pence. But ſuppoſe the foreſaid wrangler will not allow eight quarters vpon an Acre, yet ſet downe ſome fiue quarters, which commeth to fiue pound two ſhillings eight pence, the charges deducted, yet doth it exceede any one of the other by ſome three pound and eight pence.</p>
            <p>Some part of this great profits I would haue beſtowed vpon the poore to weede this one Acre, in March or A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, or ſometime before the Corne be too high, to pull vp the weedes by the rootes, and then you ſhall ſee the Corne flouriſh: keepe downe the weedes, and haue no more neede of weeding in this ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Worke and prouiſion for olde poore weake men, their wiues and children.</note>Now a word or two to incourage a poore man that hath a wife and three or foure children, that often wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth worke in ſome countries, yea though he be weake, ſickly or lame, yet he may ſet Corne with his familie, and haue ſufficient to ſerue his houſe: therefore let them fall to work cheerefully this next ſeaſon, and praiſe the Lord, for his mercie endureth for euer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
